Nikolai G. Vetr

☑ nikgvetr@stanford.edu | 📞 +1 (602) 578-9196 | in linkedin.com/in/nikolai-vetr | 🖸 github.com/NikVetr

Summary _

Computational biologist and data scientist focused on Bayesian statistics, multi-omic data integration, and machine learning methods development. Extensive experience developing and evaluating novel statistical models and computational tools to address complex biological questions across varied domains.

Education _

PhD University of California, Davis

Anthropology + Population Biology + Data Science & Informatics

2020

BA Vanderbilt University

Dissertation: "Exploring and Extending Multivariate Brownian Diffusion Models of Phenotypic Evolution for Bayesian Phylogenetic Inference"

Earth Environmental Sciences + Ecology, Evolution & Organismal Biology

- Departmental Honors, summa cum laude

2013

Experience ____

Stanford University – Postdoctoral Researcher

Stanford, CA | 2020 - Present

Montgomery Lab (Pathology, Genetics, Biomedical Data Science)

- Integrated differential expression results with drug, perturbation target, and biobank databases with approx. 1TB of input data to provide causal inferential insights into the results of a large-scale animal experiment (Nat. Comms., 2024).
- Made key contributions to multi-omic analysis (GWAS, eQTL, transcriptomics, proteomics, ATAC-seq) of exercise response data for the MoTrPAC, identifying molecular transducers of physical activity (Nature, 2024).
- Developed novel Bayesian probability models and analysis pipelines for differential allele-specific expression analysis in ovarian cancer using high-depth mmPCR-seq (ASHG, 2024).
- Derived and implemented powerful and efficient computational methods for Bayesian data analysis, including novel correlation matrix prior and proposal distributions, efficient model reparameterizations, and code translation utilities.
 - Runtime and power improved by multiple orders of magnitude vs. conventional parameterizations on typical datasets (eg 10-50x for multilevel GLMs with K = 3 sets of "random intercepts", contingency tensors, iterated filtration enrichment estimation).

Rethink Priorities – Board President / Director

Global | 2023 - Present

- Led Board of Directors for research non-profit focused on cause prioritization, overseeing strategic direction, executive performance, and financial governance, leveraging data modeling skills (eg time series of fundraising performance).
- Provided statistical consulting on Bayesian modeling, causal inference, and data analysis for projects spanning GenAI, global health, survey response data, and computational biology.

University of California, Davis – Instructor / Consultant

Davis, CA | 2015 - 2020

- Developed and delivered lectures, labs, and assessments for upper-division courses in Human and Primate Biology.
- Founded and led interdisciplinary Applied Bayesian Statistics Research Cluster (70+ members), providing training and consultation on Bayesian and Deep Learning methods to the academic research community.
- Led workshops and served as a certified Carpentries instructor, teaching coding and data science skills to researchers.
- Won multiple awards for biology and data science outreach and teaching activities.

Technical Skills

Programming: R, Stan, BASH, Python, C++, JS, Git, AWS, RevBayes

Statistical / ML Methods: Bayesian Inference, Monte Carlo Methods, Multilevel Models, GLMs / GLMMs, Time Series Analysis, Causal Inference, Optimization, Computer Vision, NLP, Measurement Error, Sparse Estimation, Outlier Detection, Signal Processing, Spatial Autocorrelation, Missing Data Imputation, ODEs, D/CTMCs

Bioinformatics: Multi-omic Data Integration (Genomics, Transcriptomics, Proteomics, Epigenomics), Association Mapping, ASE Analysis, Population and Quantitative Genetics, Interactive / Dynamic Data Visualization, HPC

Domain Knowledge: Molecular Biology, Human Genetics, Exercise Physiology, Evolutionary Biology, Human Anatomy

Languages: English (Native), Russian (Native), Spanish (Proficient)